They were ambushed and murdered on the
road to the hotel. It was a human rights
investigation into a massacre. That's
dangerous
nationalism. 2,000 people suffocated.
Guys, it was a little bit of a miracle
that we even get this interview edited
and out. John was dealing with like a 1
megabyte upload. So, pardon all of the
pauses. Matt couldn't take part in this
conversation. But if you like hearing
John Kuryaku, and I know that's why
you're here, this is another fun one.
So, uh, one last note before you start
listening. We get shadowbanned whenever
we talk to John like no one's business.
Every every little clip that we try to
make is is tough. So, we introduce a new
sort of way to cover up some of the
things he says, you'll notice it. Uh,
you know, we're doing our best. If you
have any suggestions, let us know. But
welcome to the Awesome Map podcast. And
here's John Kuryaku. John, good to see
you again. Good to see you.
Did you you were just out of town. What
were you doing? Oh, I I've been very
very fortunate in that um a production
company in London has uh signed me to do
a hundred speeches over the next year
all around the world. So, this was the
second leg. No way. Of my speaking tour.
Yeah. Yeah. We're We have 38 dates.
What's it focused on? My career. It's
funny that they saw they saw one of
these podcasts that I did that went
viral. It was Danny Jones. And then
Danny Jones led to Daltton Fischer. And
then Daltton Fischer led to Julian uh
Dory.
And they said that I was a good
storyteller. And they the these guys um
sent uh the the two DEA agents who
killed Pablo Escobar on a speaking tour
and they made bank all around the world.
So they asked if I wanted to do
something similar. I said yes. and uh
and we've started. So, it's been great.
Is this with Unified TV or is it is it
someone else? That's a completely
different thing. U this is with it's a
thing called Tigers Lane
Studios. Unified TV is where I have this
uh this TV show once a week. It's uh CIA
declassified. It's uh we take these
declassified CIA documents and tell like
historical stories um using the
documents. the Berlin airlift and the
Aende overthrow and the Iran coup and
stuff like that.
What has anything popped out that's been
really surprising as you've been going
over? Are these recently released
documents or these older ones? Some of
them are recent. Most of them are older.
Uh but they're buried in places like the
National Security Archives at George
Washington University or at presidential
libraries. You know, if if a president
takes documents with him for his
presidential library, those documents
don't go to the national archives. So,
there's no centralized repository for
any of these things. You have to just go
to one after the other. Especially if
you're a PhD student and you need
something that's comprehensive, it's
hard to do.
So, there there really are libraries
that you have to go to to get valuable
documents. Is that right? Yeah. You have
to physically go there. That is. And
then for the National Archives, um, most
of what somebody working on a PhD would
need is at this gigantic storage
facility in Green Belt, Maryland. So,
you've got to make an appointment, go
out there. Uh, you can't bring your
phone in. You have to use their copy
machines. They charge a lot of money.
It's It's not easy.
I've I've been diving deep into like
Thomas Townson Brown. Are you familiar
with Thomas Townson Brown? No, I sure am
not.
He He was a guy that was working with
the National Research Labs of the Navy,
the Navy Research Labs, I guess, on
anti-gravity tech. And the author of one
of the books I'm reading had to go to
all of these libraries. And I started
wondering like, is the truth actually
just hidden in plain sight? I I think
everyone wonders about the Illuminati,
you know, hiding everything from us. But
I wonder if it's more of just
bureaucracy hiding it from us. I'll tell
you a story. Yeah, you probably know it,
but after we captured Abu Zuba in
Pakistan, a buddy of mine and I were
driving from Pashaw to uh Islamabad. It
was late at night and we drove past the
Taliban embassy. It was the last
remaining Taliban embassy in the world.
It was in Pashaw even though Pashaw is
not the capital of Pakistan. And
um and my friend said my friend was a
detective with the Port Authority of New
York and New Jersey. He was on loan to
the FBI. And he said he said, "Look at
these look at these [__] They have
the they have the nerve to fly the
Taliban flag like they're sticking it in
our face." And I said, "Yeah, can you
imagine?" And he said, "You know what we
should do? We should break in there and
we should steal everything that they
have." And I said, "Oh my god, that
would be so much fun." And then I
thought, no, you know what? That's
exactly what we should do. So we drove
back to Islamad. I went on the computer.
I wrote a cable to headquarters, request
permission to raid the Taliban embassy
in Pashawer and steal everything. The
next day they said, "No way. Go with
God. Go with God. We requisitioned a
couple of vans."
We drove back to Pashawer, middle of the
night, picked the lock in 5 seconds,
busted in, and we stole everything that
wasn't bolted to the floor, which was
everything. And we stole everything. And
the reason I'm telling you this is much
of what we we took, it filled two of the
vans, uh, were documents. About 4 days
later, my buddy comes up to our floor
and the embassy and says, "Um, hey, we
found something that's very disturbing."
And he hands me this file folder and
it's full of phone bills from the from
the Taliban
embassy. And these bills
show
dozens, hundreds of calls to numbers all
across the United States. Bethesda,
Maryland, Kansas City, Fargo, North
Dakota,
LA, all over the country. And they stop
on December the
10th, and then they start up again
slowly on December, I'm sorry, on
September
16th. So, I send a KO to headquarters. I
said, "Be advised. We found this. It's
very disturbing." Um, and they said,
"Make sure the FBI has the original.
send a copy to us and give a copy to the
Pakistanis. So I did because 911 was
still an open criminal investigation and
so the FBI got the originals. I go back
to CIO in May of
um of
uh
2002 and I run into one of the FBI guys
and I said, "Hey, what happened to the
uh what happened to the um phone bills,
the Taliban phone bills?" And he said,
"Uh, you know what, man? We haven't done
anything with them because we can't find
a Poshtu
translator. I said, "A posashtu
translator? They were in English. That's
how I knew that they were phone bills. I
don't speak
Poshtu." He's like, "Oh, right." Yeah.
Nobody's even opened the box. He said,
"This is like six months
later." So, another And for real, they
just hadn't opened the box. It He wasn't
covering for it. He for real, no one had
opened this box. No, nobody had opened
the box. So I resigned two years
later. 5 years after the raid, I run
into one of the FBI agents that went
with us at the at the mall at Tyson's
Corner Mall in Tyson's Corner,
Virginia. And I said, "Hey, whatever
happened with those Taliban numbers?"
And he said, "You know what, buddy?" He
said, "I hate to tell you, but nobody
ever opened that box." And they sent it
out to a FBI um storage facility in
Maryland. And just like the closing
scene in Raiders of the Lost Ark, it's
sitting on some shelf somewhere in this
storage facility. Nobody's ever opened
it. They could have been living among
us, these cells all across America. and
the FBI never even opened the
box. So, no, I to answer your initial
question, I think
that most of what we see is
incompetence. It's not conspiracy
conspiracy. It's just booery, you know,
that's what it comes down to. Yeah.
Well, it means there's infinite content
to be discovered by people just going in
the National Archives. This is a this is
really a call to arms for journalists,
isn't it? It's like go sit in the
libraries. Go figure this out. You can
say that again. Wow. You know, I was
going Well, I want I would love to I'm
sorry. Go ahead.
No, go ahead. I was going to say I was
going through Greek archives on this
last trip and I find this document. It
was a property dispute that involved my
my
greatgrandfather. And at the bottom of
the property dispute, it says that his
first wife, and it named her, has no
claim. I'm like, what do they mean his
first
wife? Are they saying he was married
twice? Like, nobody in my family knows.
Yeah, it sounds like it. So, it's all,
you know, the truth is out there. You
just have to look for it.
That's interesting. Your your parents
came from Greece, is that right? Was
your dad Giannis car? That was my
grandfather. Your grandparents did. Oh,
okay. Okay. They all came from the
other. Oh, so he was the one.
It was his father. And he's the one that
you were finding maybe was married
twice. No, it it was his father. Um, and
the funny thing
is my grandfather was one of 18
children. And so how my
great-grandfather had the time to be
married before
that, I I have no idea. No idea. Yeah.
Set the bar high. Yeah.
Yeah, I that kind of I was wondering
about you yesterday and I was thinking
like John sort of comes from a different
heritage and yet it seems like you sort
of embody American exceptionalism. Oh,
thank you. In in your life in my eyes,
how do you how did that happen? How how
did a a Greek family come over and
produce you who's who's very much uh
rooting for America? Oh, yeah.
my um my grandparents my dad's parents
came in 1931 and my mom's parents came
in
1934 and um to hear my grandfather my
dad's father tell the story Franklin
Roosevelt was like personally standing
there at Ellis Island to shake his hand
and give him an American passport and a
job at US Steel in Pittsburgh. And so
until he died in
1978, he had a framed picture of
Franklin Roosevelt on top of the TV. I
still have it. I have it in my
den. And so he was so
grateful for the opportunities that he
had coming to America that that he
wanted all of us in the next two
generations to
be grateful. And that's why I only
considered public service. I didn't I
never ever gave any thought about going
into the private sector. It was all
about public service. But my grandfather
my grandfather was like my best friend
when I was a little kid. And
um he was grateful of course, but he
also believed that it was up to all of
us to keep our leaders on the straight
and narrow. He told me a story once
about about calling in sick once to the
mill in Pittsburgh and secretly
attending a Sacko and Venzetti rally. I
don't know if you guys know who Sacko
and Benzetti were, but they were two
anarchists, two Italian anarchists from
Massachusetts who were wrongly accused
of robbing a
payroll and they were convicted and
sentenced to death because a a policeman
was shot. Well, in the course of appeal
after appeal after appeal, it became
clear that they hadn't done this. They
were anarchists, but they hadn't
committed this crime. Uh but the public
wanted blood because they were so afraid
of communism and anarchism at the time
that they were executed uh in
Massachusetts and their bodies shipped
back to Italy. Well, you know, being a
working man and a and a an economic
refugee just like Sacko and Venzetti
were, um my grandfather felt it was
important to risk everything. He could
have been deported for going to a
meeting like this, but it was that
important to him that we that we hold
our leaders to account. And so he made
sure that I
understood the the reason and that I
understood the issue behind the reason.
Do you think that there's like a losing
sense of nationalism these days that is
actually required to keep a country
together?
Oh, you know what? I think it's the
opposite. I think we're seeing this this
uber nationalism to the point where it's
it's actually dangerous. I think it's
dangerous.
Uhuh. You know,
when when people can be prosecuted for
their political beliefs, when when
when a federal government can shut down
or or attack a
university because they allow
constitutionally protected freedom of
speech. That's dangerous
nationalism. I'm I'm genuinely worried
about it. You know, it comes in in waves
and cycles. We saw this with uh let's
say Huey Long and Father Cochland in the
1930s.
Um we saw probably the the lowest point
of it uh after the assassination of of
JFK, but it's back with a vengeance and
it makes us more divided.
Well, it almost becomes authoritarian.
Yeah, exactly. If you start monitoring
what people can say, what universities
are allowed to think. Yes. Yeah. It's a
very slippery
slope. Yeah. I'm curious how you see
that. Like where where do you think are
the lynch pins that that hold the
freedoms together? I guess what are the
most necessary things that we we keep
going as the American experiment is is
surging forward. It's all
about presidential respect for the
Constitution. We can't even trust the
the Supreme Court anymore to respect
president. Um, so I'm I'm genuinely
worried about that.
But, you know, I Why do you say that?
I'm I'm a little
bit I'm a little bit less informed about
Supreme Court decisions. Time time was
when you know, the Supreme Court made a
a ruling that was it. It was the law of
the land. Not that we would keep
chipping away at it year after year
after year until it was overturned. Now,
if we're talking about something like
pie versus Ferguson, yeah, of course.
Well, I mean, some decisions are just
clearly wrong, wrong, wrong. Or
Koramatsu, wrong, wrong, wrong. But
otherwise, you know, this this idea of
appointing not just not guardians of the
constitution but political ideologues to
the Supreme Court, I think is very very
dangerous. And and it encourages
separatism and
division. And look at look at the
political system we've given ourselves
as recently as a 100 years ago. And in
political terms, that's pretty recent.
We had viable third parties like
multiple third parties where where you
know the progressive party was getting
people elected to Congress uh or getting
people elected governor. Um before that
going back to the civil war there were
six different political parties
represented in Congress. One of my
favorite examples is Solomon P. Chase.
He was he was Abraham Lincoln secretary
of the treasury and he had been the
governor of Ohio. He was a Democrat. He
was a Republican. He was a radical
Republican. He was a states rights. He
was a no nothing. He was in he was in
all six different parties. Every time he
got pissed off or every time he had a a
policy difference with the leadership of
his party, he would switch
parties. And we we don't and can't do
that anymore because we've whittleled
ourselves down to two parties, which in
my mind are just two sides of the same
coin. And we we shun third parties.
We've got third parties. We've got the
Libertarians and the Greens. We've got
the Reform Party, the Unity Party. But,
you know, people will tell you, "Oh,
you're just wasting your vote. You're
throwing away your vote. Oh, I just vote
for the lesser of two evils." Well, my
god, the lesser of two evils is still
evil. I don't want to vote for
evil. And so,
yeah.
And that coin seems to be driven by sort
of corportocracy, doesn't it? It feels
like the corporations Exactly. Have just
taken over the both sides. Both sides.
They're both corporate parties. How do
you undo that? Yeah, I know. I don't
know if you can unless you you overturn
Citizens United and institute uh public
financing of political campaigns. That's
one way of doing it. But otherwise, you
have to buy your way onto the stage, and
that just doesn't work. I campaigned
with Gary Johnson um in
2016. We went to 12 states together. He
he was he used to be the Republican
governor of New Mexico, but then he was
the Libertarian uh nominee for
president. And he told me
that that the Libertarians could never
compete because they have one
benefactor. He's like the the canned
tomato king of California, whoever he
is. And he gave the party enough money
that they bought this Winnebago. and we
drove to these 12 states in the
Winnebago and then that's it. You can't
buy TV advertising. You can't buy social
media advertising. You ne you can never
get on the debate stage. You guys are
probably a little bit too young, but the
debates used to be the presidential
debates used to be run by the the League
of Women Voters. Okay? And it was always
the Democrat, the Republican, and
whatever independents were able to get
onto the ballot. So you'd have three,
sometimes four people up there in the
presidential
debates. Well, the two
parties colluded to cut out the League
of Women Voters and to make the
Presidential Commission on
Debates, which is three members of the
DNC and three members of the RNC. and
they decided that unless you poll, I
think it's
15% in three
national recognized polls, you can't get
invited. Well, nobody's going to pull
15%. Not unless you're you're, you know,
a a billionaire who's financing his own
campaign like Ross Perau was back in '
92 and 96. You can't compete. And they
did that on purpose to keep third
parties down.
Well, what that says to me, normally in
any complex system, when you have like a
bottleneck of power, whoever is on that
committee deciding who's allowed to be
on the debates, that would be a high
area of corruption just just from my
study of complex systems because it'd be
very soughta. Have is there any evidence
of corruption in specifically in those
debate processes?
You tell me if this is corruption. So,
there's this kid named David Hog you
probably have heard of. He's one of the
Parkland uh mass shooting survivors.
David Hog, God bless him. He went to
Harvard, graduated from Harvard, and
jumped right into politics. Got himself
elected one of the vice presidents of
the
DNC. and he announced that, you know,
the whole party's corrupt and he wants
to start running young young Democrats
in primaries against older established
Democrats because it's time for new
blood, right? Congress is grossly older
than the than the national average. Time
for new blood. So, what did they do?
They said, "Oh, you know what? We just
realized that the vice presidential spot
that David Hog ran for and won was
supposed to be reserved for a
lesbian. And so, uh, oh my gosh, they
threw him out last week and now they're
having a
reelection. He's not allowed to run for
his seat. Only lesbians can run. I would
call that corruption. Is that that's
real? This Yeah, this is the president
of the Democratic National and And this
is the president of which No way. No
way.
Yeah. Okay. I thought the Democrats were
were shaping up. I had been getting the
impression that they were going back,
licking their wounds and and
reorganizing. It sounds like they're
just doubling down on terrible policy.
They don't stand for
anything. That's the problem. The
Democrats don't stand for anything. And
when they do stand for something, it's
just kind of a variation of what the
Republicans stand for. I I joke all the
time when I give um interviews to the
foreign media that we have in the United
States, we have a right-wing party and
we have a farther right-wing party and
they're constantly
competing. I spoke with a Frenchman. The
French, you know, they claim to be the
sort of like they own debate. debate is
there is there seen in world history and
this Frenchman was telling me he said in
the United States you don't even have a
left he said you don't have a proper
left or a proper right you have a a
center and a center right and that's it
that's it true it's true
yeah makes yeah it's interesting well I
want to hear more about about
can you tell us about some of the um
documents you've been finding in the
archives that that sounds so interesting
to me to know that there's documents
about almost like conspiracies, but
they're just sitting in national
archives that no one goes and looks at
because no one looks at real paper
anymore. The the the best one was the
Iran coup of 1953, right? The
conventional wisdom is that we we
overthrow we overthrew Muhammad Wasadc,
the democratically elected uh president
of of Iran. We we replaced him with the
Shaw of Iran who was eventually
overthrown in 1979. and that we did this
as a favor to the British because the
British were stealing Iranian oil and
they wanted to continue to steal Iranian
oil. So you go into the archives and you
realize that we were actually a little
bit late to the game. See the the
history that everybody, you know, knows
is that Kermit Roosevelt
uh who was the uh what was Kermit? He
was the the fourth son of Teddy
Roosevelt, the fifth son of whatever he
was. He was a son of Teddy Roosevelt,
highly highly honored and decorated CIA
officer. Um that he engineered the coup
that overthrew
Mosettic. That's what he told everybody
until he died. That's not what the
documents show. The documents show that
this was an MI6 operation, but the
British weren't sure that they could
pull it off themselves. And so they
needed American money. American money to
finance riots, anti-government riots,
and to arm people who wanted to
overthrow Mosadic.
So, the brainchild of this whole plan
was an MI6 officer who never ever gave a
single interview ever. And then he died
in the 70s or the
80s. Um, in the meantime, Kermit
Roosevelt, as soon as he retired, just
started yakking and then wrote a book
like how I overthrew the Iranian
government. It's like, dude, I
understand you want your own place in
history, but you didn't overthrow the
Iranian government. Not according to the
CIA documents. You wish you did. You
tried to help to overthrow the
government, but this was a British
operation. The thing is is that Kermit
Roosevelt was so successful in
convincing people that the CIA overthrew
Mosadic
that when the Iranian revolution finally
took place in uh well beginning in
February of 1979
um it was the American embassy that was
stormed. It they were American diplomats
that were that were captured and held
hostage for 444 days. And here we
are 46 years later and we still don't
have diplomatic relations with
Iran. In the meantime, the British are
perfectly good to go. No, no worries.
Yeah. Why is it that America can't
establish relations with Iran? Is is
Russia involved? Is it is it left over
from the Cold War? Like what's going on?
In part, well, the the Iranians hate us
not as as a people. They they hate us as
a government. Um and they distrust us.
They have good reason to. U they're not
innocent because we hate and distrust
them too also with good reason. But at a
higher level, Iranian relations with
Russia and China are
excellent. And neither Russia nor China
respect US sanctions on Iran. So they're
helping to upgrade the Iranian uh oil uh
oil sector. They're dredging Iran's
harbors. The Chinese are buying whatever
goods the Iranians can produce and vice
versa. I have a very close friend who
goes to Iran twice a year and she was
there just a month ago and she tells me
every time she comes back, the Iranians
lack for
nothing. Nothing. Our sanctions on them,
zero effect. Nothing. They don't need
us. Wow. So every time you hear, "Oh,
we're putting new sanctions on Iran."
First of all, there are no new real
sanctions you can put on Iran.
Everything's sanctioned. So when we hear
Treasury saying, well, we're going to
put new sanctions on Iran. Those
sanctions are like, if Matt ever tries
to open a checking account, he will be
denied. He's under sanction. Okay. Matt
doesn't give a [__] to open a a checking
account in Iran,
you know. In Iran. Yeah. Yeah. So that
that's what the are they fired.
I I have a friend who's a banker and he
always says, "Show me the rules. I'll
show you how to break them." Like the
rules were made by the rich people and
the smart people and they're always
broken by the rich people. Exactly.
Yeah. Exactly. Yeah. Precisely. So it's
just one of these things where sanctions
don't work because simply because they
just don't work. It's not because no one
involved wants them to work. It's
because there's always a way around it.
and and to that Austin, I think this is
this is important. Um Barack Obama
negotiated the JCPOA with Iran, okay,
the Iran nuclear deal
and many of the sanctions were lifted.
So as part of that um the European Union
also lifted their sanctions not just the
European Union but the UK and Japan,
Germany and and uh France which are in
the European Union. So um everybody
started trading with
Iran. Donald Trump pulls out of the
JCPOA. So we're we don't have any trade
with Iran at all. Nothing. But we also
have a law in this country that says
that if you do business with Iran, we
have to sanction
you. Okay? He unilaterally pulled out of
the JCPOA. So now legally we have to
impose sanctions on the UK, Germany,
France, Japan, and every other country
that does business with Iran. We're not
going to do that. Not ever.
And so that makes our sanctions and our
silly secondary sanctions law
moot and the Iranians laugh at us
because we've put ourselves in a corner
that we can't get out of
more bureaucracy. How much of this is
really actually about them having
nuclear weapons or or how much of it is
about something else? The CIA has
published three national intelligence
estimates over the last 25 years. All
three concluding that the Iranians do
not want and are not seeking a nuclear
weapon. That's what the intelligence Why
is that the only thing on the news about
Iran? I know. I I don't understand then.
Well, because it's constantly about, you
know, yeah, they they they are um
enriching uranium. Uh, first it was 3
and a half%. Now after we pulled out
it's 67%, well you need like 95% for for
a weapon. Well, yeah, but they could
turn the 67% into 95% in a matter of
weeks. Yeah, but they haven't. And our
politicians have been saying for the
last 30 years that the Iranians are are
six months away from a nuclear
weapon. For 30
years, you know, the Trump has an offer
on the table that uh that the Iranians
can continue to enrich uranium for the
purpose of a civilian nuclear power
program if the uranium is kept in a
third country, probably the United Arab
Emirates. I think the Iranians would
agree to that. We're we're going to have
to wait and see, but I think that that
is going to be good enough.
Can I ask you a really ignorant
question? Do they is does Israel have
nuclear weapon capabilities? Thousand%
yes.
Yes. Okay. It seems like they're always
left off the list when Yeah, they are.
They're they're not people consider
that. Okay. They're not signitories to
the non-prololiferation the nuclear
non-prololiferation treaty. They just
told the UN go [__] themselves over
non-prololiferation.
And not only did they develop their own
nuclear uh weapons program, but when
South Africa fell, when the when the
apartheid government in South Africa
fell, um they gave the Israelis all of
their nuclear weapons so as not to h to
fall into the hands of black people. Oh
yeah. So, you know, this is something
that the Israelis have never admitted
to. Everybody knows they have nuclear
weapons. I was on the Pierce Morgan show
a couple of weeks ago um debating Alan
Dersowitz and a guy named Danny Atome,
the former head of Mossad. And Pice
asked him, "Does Israel have nuclear
weapons?" And he smiled and he said,
"All I can tell you is what the prime
minister has said." And the prime
minister has said that we will not
comment on nuclear weapons.
So there it is. So we have a very clear
double standard with Iran and Israel.
It's like Israel, everybody knows. Okay.
I I still can't understand the problem
with Iran. No, it's it's irrational. We
also have a double standard with both
Pakistan and India because we have good
relations with both Pakistan and India
and and very significant trade relations
with Pakistan and India. They built
nuclear weapons with the help of
allegedly with the help of North Korea
um to shoot at each other. And we're
like, "Yeah, we don't want you guys to
shoot at each other these nuclear
weapons, but we really like both of you,
and we'd like to trade with both of you,
so we're going to pretend everything's
fine. What about sanctions on that?"
Gosh, you don't hear about it at all.
It's not Iran, so we don't talk about
it. That's it. There's no process.
There's no consistency. No, none. None
whatsoever.
None whatsoever. It's like I'm I mean my
thesis is that the US is now a
multi-headed beast. Like there is no
centralized power. The president doesn't
have all power anymore, which is, you
know, it was never designed to have all
power, but there's not even like a level
of government that feels like it's a
consistent deciding force. Yeah. Yeah.
This just kind of fits in with it.
There's multiple heads probably have
multiple motives and they're not really
coordinating too much. It makes me
wonder, is the United States too big? Is
it too big to have a government of the
size of the US? Yeah. How does it how do
you fix it?
Yeah, I I think it's the the political
process that's broken. We need to have a
robust and healthy civil service. Donald
Trump has been attacking that and I
understand why, but we need to have a a
non-political or apolitical
uh civil service. Um but you're right.
You know, we have three equal branches
of government and right now it's
offkilter. They aren't equal. You've got
a very strong executive. you have a very
weak legislative and then you have a a
judicial that's trying to to fill the
void. I think it's going to go back to
its its you know its
uh
equality but it's going to it's going to
take a long time. And again I think
another part of the problem is
this this phony two-party system that we
have. It just doesn't allow for for
disscent. It doesn't even allow for for
investigation. I'll give you another
example.
Um, I used to be the I used to be the
senior uh investigator on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee when John
Kerry was the committee's chairman
and I did an investigation. It was a
human rights investigation into a
massacre that took place in Afghanistan
called the Dash Delele Massacre. And I
had evidence that two CIA officers were
were present at the massacre when 2,000
Taliban prisoners were
suffocated.
2,000 people suffocated. Yeah. At once.
So I wrote, "How do they suffocate? I
mean, how do you suffocate 2,000
people?" two on
on October, I'm sorry, on November 30th
and December 1st of 2001, 2,000 Taliban
soldiers gave themselves up to the to
the Northern Alliance. The Northern
Alliance called us and said, "They just
on Moss, they just gave up. What do we
do?" Well, there there were no prisons
in Afghanistan big enough to hold 2,000
people all at once. So we told them,
"Put them on trucks and take them out
into the desert and hold them there
until we can divide them up and send
them to different prisons around the
country."
So what they did is they put them inside
container trucks, but they didn't poke
any arrow hose and they didn't give them
any food or water. Oh no. Of the 2,000
people that were boxed up, the 14
survived. And one of the survivors told
me that the bodies fell out of the
trucks like sardines from a can.
But I learned
that there were two CI officers on site
at the box
up. So I wanted to know were were they
ordered to kill these 2,000 Taliban
soldiers or was this an accident or a
[__] or what was this? So I wrote a
letter. Carrie signed it and I sent it
to the CIA asking for class for uh
clarification. About six weeks later, a
colleague of mine came into my office
and said, "Oh, hey, uh, you got a you
got a response from the agency to your
letter." And I said, "I didn't see any
response from the agency. I just checked
my mail an hour ago." He said, "Yeah,
they classified it top secret." And at
the time I only had a secret clearance
because I was waiting for my upgraded
clearances to come through. And I said,
'What's it say? He says, uh, it says,
'Go [__]
yourself. So Carrie came down to my
office and he's like, yeah, you need to
end this, uh, this investigation. And
then my my immediate boss came up to me.
He's like, you don't understand. You're
not really here to investigate stuff.
You're here to help John Kerry become
Secretary of State.
But I kept investigating [__] that was
uncomfortable for the Obama
administration.
Yeah, I can imagine. Yeah. Well, c can I
ask you a personal question? Like you're
you're going on TV no fear. You're
telling even a story like that I would
imagine could be potentially construed
as a war crime if if you know if if it
were investigated further. Who knows?
Yes. What? What is your stance? I I
mean, how how do you not have you
already were thrown in jail once. How
how do you not have fear of of talking
about these things anymore?
There is a legal definition of
whistleblowing. It is bringing to light
any evidence of waste, fraud, abuse,
illegality, or threats to the public
health or public safety. And so, I
embrace it. I have no reason to try to
protect the war criminals that I've
worked for or worked with or people
perpetuating crimes against humanity. I
have a I have a
very what's the
word? I believe that the United States
is special. I believe in the idea of
American exceptionalism. I'm not an
American exceptionalist, but I believe
that the country was created so that it
it could be
exceptional. And I view these people as
anti-American,
unamerican, where they're more concerned
for their own well-being and their own,
you know, attaining higher office in
life than they are for what the
Constitution laid out for us.
You know, Ronald Reagan said at the 1984
Republican convention that the United
States is a shining city on a
hill, and I believe that he was right.
It it should be a shining city on a
hill. And many people overseas see us as
a shining city on a hill. That's what we
should strive to be. And so, yeah, if I
if I see waste, fraud, abuse,
illegality, or threats to the public
health or public safety, I'm calling it
out. And I I concluded years ago that
that if I do it all the
time, people will miss me if I somehow
disappear. I love that. Please keep
doing it and thank you for doing it
because if it weren't for people who had
the information sharing it, we would
never we would never be able to know
about these things. Yeah. Where are some
areas right now in the world where maybe
uh like like the Taliban and things
going on in Afghanistan were very hot
back, you know, it was a very hot zone
back in like the early 2000s. Where are
those hot zones right now? Oh, now it's
mostly the Sahel and uh and Somalia.
People, the American people have no idea
we are at war in the Sahel and Somalia.
The the Sahel is that that I didn't know
that that strip along the uh the Sahara
Desert. It's like um you know Moretania,
Chad, Nishair, places like that. We are
at war fighting ISIS and al-Qaeda. There
we have we have untold number of special
forces that are active in in actual
combat on a day-to-day basis. And in
Somalia, we're at war with the Somali
mostly using drones which we fly out of
Djibouti nearby. But that's another
place that people just don't realize
we're actually fighting. Every once in a
while, you'll see a little blip in the
New York Times, the Washington Post,
saying that, "Oh, this Navy Seal was
killed in a training accident." There
are no training accidents. They're being
killed in combat. We just don't want to
admit that there's combat ongoing. If
there were people over there that were
witnessing atrocities, do you open up
your door to allow people to come and
and reveal that to you first and get
help with with breaking out into the
public? Literally, how would that how
would that work if you were special
forces right now? Right. So, literally
every single day, literally, I get
emails from people, potential
whistleblowers, who want to know where
to go, who they should talk to. And the
answer should be easy, and it's not. You
should be able to go through your chain
of command and be protected by the
National Whistleblower Act or the
Federal Whistleblower Act. But
whistleblowers in national security are
exempt from its protections. And so if
you report, oh, you know, on on
illegalities, your career's over.
There's a good chance you're going to go
to prison. You have to seriously weigh
the consequences here. But what you
should
do, if you could, in a perfect world, is
go to your supervisor, then the the um
uh inspector general, then the uh
congressional oversight committees. And
most of the time, I'll give you an
example. Tom Drake, heroic whistleblower
from NSA, great friend of mine. Tom
reported um illegality first to the
first to his his boss. His boss told
him, "You're new here. You need to mind
your own business." Then he went to the
inspector general. The inspector general
wasn't read into the compartment. And so
he he's like, "I I don't know what
you're talking about." Then he went to
the general counsel. The general counsel
said, "Buddy, this is way over your pay
grade. You need to stop." Then he went
to the Pentagon inspector general
because NSA is a DoD agency. The
Pentagon Inspector General reported him
to NSA and said, "You have a rogue
employee you need to watch out for."
Then he went to the Congressional
Oversight Committee. No way. the House
Permanent Select Committee on
Intelligence and reported it and they
arrested him and charged him with nine
felonies, including seven counts of
espionage. The whole case fell apart the
night before the trial began. But he
lost his job. He lost his pension. He
lost his clearance. He lost his wife. He
ended up spending the next eight years
at the Apple Store in Bethesda,
Maryland, working in the Genius Bar.
This this guy was one of the country's
leading experts in internet
privacy. That's what they do to you. And
this is really concerning. Like how do
we open up the doors? Does it have to be
through grassroots like YouTube channels
or does a person need to start a YouTube
channel to get out in front of the
message? I think it has to be that way.
I think yes. I think yes. And another
thing that has to be done like right
away is that Congress needs to rewrite
the Espionage Act. The Espionage Act was
written in
1917 to combat German saboturs during
the First World War. It has never been
meaningfully updated. Never. It doesn't
even mention classified information
because the classification system wasn't
created until the 1950s. It just talks
about national defense information
without actually explaining what that
means, national defense information. And
so we need a new espionage act that
allows for what's called an affirmative
defense that would allow whistleblower
to say, "Yes, I released the
information, but here's why I did it. I
did it in the public interest, and now
you can't do that. Straight to prison."
Is there a system in place where private
contractors are being sent into battle
zones so that secrets could be held
better because they're in private
companies as opposed to in the in the
official military? Um,
yes. Yes. And that's a problem
because the um Federal Documents Act
mandates that all documents be
preserved, right? You have to preserve
everything. That's why if it's a private
company talking to a member of a private
company, what where's the document? The
government doesn't have it. It's it's a
corporate document. Even worse, when the
Secretary of Defense, the National
Security Adviser, the Director of
National Intelligence are using a
commercial chat app like Signal, that's
a violation of the Federal Documents
Act. You can't do that because people
have to be able to file a Freedom of
Information Act request on the record,
but the record's not on a commercial
app. It's not a document.
So, the Espionage Act needs to be
include needs to include the secrecy
levels and stipulations for private
corporation communication. Oh, I think
so. Yeah, I think so. Okay. Do you see
yourself as being a part of a group that
would help rewrite that at any point?
like how how do we how do we get the
people like you who are interested to
actually rewrite this? Honestly, Austin,
I would jump at the chance if if a if a
president were to call me and say, "Hey,
help us, you know, rewrite
this." Every national security
whistleblower I know, you know, Jeffrey
Sterling, Bill Benny, Kirk Web, Tom
Drake, Justin Raak, everybody that I
know would jump at the chance to do
something like that.
Ilhan, Omar, and it's a perfect group to
do it. Yeah, it's perfect time. Elhan
Omar is the only person with the guts to
have proposed an updated um espionage
act. She did it in the current Congress
and in the previous Congress and they
just go to subcommittee to die a quiet
death. You know, she said to me one
time, she said the reason why she can't
get any co-sponsors on these bills, she
goes, "Can you imagine going back to
your home district and saying, I'm going
to make it more difficult to prosecute
people for espionage.
Come on." Yeah. Vote for that. That's
not a good narrative. Yeah. She's like,
"You and I both know it needs to be
done. It needed to be done 75 years ago,
and nobody's done it. But you're not
going to win any votes that way.
What What was her interest in it? Was
she appointed to a committee or was it a
personal interest that she just took on?
A personal interest in whistleblowing
that that she she just believes that
national security whistleblowers have
taken it on the chin and that the entire
system needs to be
changed. Let let me add something to
that actually. So Ed Snowden once told
me that he would be willing to come home
and go to prison if he could stand up in
the courtroom and explain why he did
what he did. So I I introduced him to my
attorneys. Oh my gosh. He hired my
attorneys and they negotiated a deal
with the Justice Department.
But Ed
insisted he's he's willing to come home
and go to prison, but he wants to
explain why he did what he did. And DOJ
said absolutely not. And so he's never
come back. And here we are, what, 12
years
later, and nothing has changed.
No way.
Yeah. And when the power of your words
are more powerful than the punishment
they're going to bestow upon you, that
means it needs to be said. It has to be
said. That's right.
That's a lot, man. That's a lot to think
about. Awful. Uh, can you help can you
help walk us through what's going on in
the Red Sea? I keep seeing all these
headlines like US battleships lined up
in the Red Sea. What what what exactly
is going on in that part of the world
and and especially on the water? Why do
we have so many battleships over there?
That's actually a very complicated
question. So that there are two policy
reasons why we're in the Red Sea. One is
the Houthis in Yemen. We can talk about
them pretty quickly. The other is
Israel.
So the Houthies. So Yemen has been a a
basket case of a
country for the last 35 years. When I
when I first started at the CIA, there
were two Yemens. There was the Yemen
Arab Republic, also called North Yemen,
and then there was the People's
Democratic Republic of Yemen, which was
South Yemen. It was a communist
satellite state during the Soviet days.
Um they uh they merged in April of 1990.
People were literally dancing in the
street. Um it was a very exciting time
to be in Yemen. It really was. I've been
to Yemen five
times. And then afterwards, uh, things
weren't really working out the way they
were hoping things would work out. Like,
there's no real economic benefit to the
two of them merging together. They're
still like the third poorest country on
Earth. Nothing's really happening. Then
they did something so colossally
stupid that all these years later, I
still shake my head 34 years
later. On August 2nd,
1990, Iraq invaded
Kuwait. Yemen happened to be on the
United Nations Security Council at the
time in one of the rotating positions.
So, Secretary of State James Baker said,
"Look, we are going to attack Iraq.
We're going to force them out of uh out
of Kuwait, and the Russians are with us
and the Chinese are with us on a use of
force vote. So, there's not going to be
a veto. Either you're with us or you're
against us."
What would possess
them to join Cuba as the only other
country in the world to vote no on a use
of force to liberate Kuwait? What ended
up happening was within 24 hours, the
Saudis expelled all six million Yemeni
guest workers.
Kuwait, Bahrain, Qatar, Oman, and the
United Arab Emirates did the same with
another million. People were living in
cardboard boxes. I saw this with my own
eyes. Living in cardboard boxes, in
shanties with tin
roofs, starvation was a problem. Couple
that with the fact that until the late
1970s, Yemen was a net food
exporter. But then in the late 70s, the
government began to subsidize water. And
so literally everybody changed their
crops from food to gat. Gat is a shrub
that people chew like the cocoa leaf and
it gives you a jolt. Yeah. It's like the
national thing. Everybody in the country
chews gut. That's
fine. But your children are starving and
they have no shoes. So maybe you should
grow tomatoes or corn or wheat or
something instead of got. So 7 million
people literally overnight re-enter the
the country. It's already the poorest
country in the world. There's no water
because it's all going to gat. There's
no food because it's going to go. There
are no jobs. There are no schools. I was
there one time and the American
ambassador told me there are 14 million
people in this country. There are two
dentists. Two. Oh my gosh. That's the
kind of country it is, dude. So then a
little bit later, they're deciding, you
know, we don't really like being one
Yemen. We kind of preferred things when
it was two Yemens. And they start
launching Scud missiles on each
other and they had a civil war. And then
the North defeated the South and said,
"No, you're not going to break away.
We're still one Yemen." Well, then the
strong man Ali
Abdalis in
in North Yemen, but he was the president
of unified Yemen. He was a Saudi puppet
and I I went to Yemen in
2011 and man, it was rough. There was a
group of Korean Yeah, there was a group
of Korean diplomats that flew in a day
after I did. We're only allowed to stay
in in one hotel, right? There's this
one. It's got 30 foot walls with barbed
wire all around the hotel. It's
fortified. So, I had this armored car. I
had two chase cars and they carried me
from the airport to the
hotel. The next day, six South Korean
diplomats flew in and they were ambushed
and murdered on the road to the hotel.
A few days later, the South Korean
Intelligence Service sent a group of
investigators to figure out who did
this, and they were ambushed and killed
on the road to the
hotel. So, it's rough.
In the meantime, then the Were they
going after South Koreans in particular?
No, just going any after anybody who's
not a not a Sunni Muslim. Yeah. So, um
Okay. Yeah.
In the meantime, the Shia are a minority
in uh Yemen. They're about 25 or 30% of
the population, and they get funding and
weapons from Iran. And they decided, you
know what, this country is so weak. This
government is so weak, we could probably
take it over. And so they started using
drones to attack the capital. That was
in 2009.
Then finally in like 2016 they were
successful in overthrowing the
government and they blew up President
Salah. The the pictures are gruesome
from the from the uh the assassination
and the Houthis have taken over now.
Really the Houthies only control Sana
the capital and some of the countryside
around Sana. The rest of the country is
just in a state of chaos. But the
Houthis decided to pledge their their um
support for Hamas, which is all fine and
good. But in that decision, they decided
their words to fire on any ship owned by
Israel, controlled by Israel, on its way
to Israel, or on its way from
Israel. Okay. Wow. Well, these guys,
like I said, these guys don't even have
shoes. How are they going to know which
ship has what and is doing what and is
coming from where and going where? So
they said, "Ah, what the hell? We'll
just fire on every ship." Well, some of
those ships are painted gray. Wow. And
have a US flag flying on them and have
50 caliber guns. If it's a US Navy ship,
why in blazes are you firing on a US
Navy ship? So we we bombed the living
daylights out of the
Houthies, but
said privately,
reportedly, "How long do you spend
$100,000 to blow up a $10,000 drone?
Right? Our missiles are expensive." So,
he negotiated this deal about three
weeks ago that they're just going to
stop firing on US ships. The Israelis
were infuriated because we didn't say
anything about not firing on Israeli
ships, but that's Israel's problem.
So we've got the
Houthis and we've got Israel and that's
why we're in the Red Sea. Okay. So it's
uh I I guess we're still over there just
in case Houthies are firing on people to
try to keep peace. Yeah. Because the
what the Israelis keep threatening to do
is is to launch um missiles on Iran and
they want to launch bunker busters
because the Iranian nuclear program is
deep underground. Even the Israeli
bunker busters, oh, are probably not
strong enough or heavy enough to destroy
the Iranian facilities. And if the
Iranians don't have a nuclear weapon, by
God, they're going to have one quickly
once they're attacked. And uh and the
Israelis, you know, want us to be there
to rescue them. Well, from a policy
perspective, that's a terrible idea
because it would essentially give them
the green light to go ahead and attack
Iran if they know definitively that
we're going to protect them or we're
going to support them.
Yeah. So, on the other hand, just in
case to go it alone, right, we want to
be in the region close enough that we
could respond if we have to. Man, I
don't like that. It sounds like a a
tinder box waiting to explode, doesn't
it? It is. You know, I remember a a
senior military analyst at the CIA once
told me, "If you really want to know if
a war is going to happen, watch naval
maneuvers, especially the relocation of
carrier battle groups." He said, "If we
start moving carrier battle groups, then
we're
serious." When the Gulf War first
started in 1990,
um, up until then, we had never put a a
an aircraft carrier in the Persian Gulf.
We always said it was too shallow and it
wasn't big enough big enough for us to
turn around.
Well, once the war started, we had six
carrier battle groups in the Persian
Gulf.
So, there's a carrier battle group. So
shallow. Yeah, there's one in the Indian
Ocean. There's one in the Red Sea.
There's one in the Eastern
Mediterranean. That's That's bad. If we
send one into the Gulf or we send a
fourth
out, I'm going to be worried. Yeah,
these are basically like mobile fighting
bases that we can move around. They're
whole communities. They're like cities
of terror that are floating on the
water. That's exactly what Yeah. It's
very important to know where those are.
Yes, indeed.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I would never shoot at
one of those. That's That's insane. No.
Well, no way. I wouldn't either.
Not a chance. What What's going on with
Taiwan? Like two years ago, all the
ships, all all the maps I was seeing was
was these sort of like people ideulating
on where the ships were, how they were
going to head towards Taiwan, and how
Taiwan was going to defend itself. Now,
it seems like everything shifted over to
the Red Sea. At least on my newsfeed,
and I know everybody has different news
feeds, but what's what's going on with
Taiwan still? Well, you know, the thing
is what's going on in Taiwan really is
what's going on in the United States
because Taiwan's not worried about any
imminent Chinese
threat. We've always
recognized Taiwan as a part of China.
And both the Taiwanese and the Chinese
say that someday eventually through
negotiations they will rejoin,
reconnect. We're the ones that keep
yelling about the Chinese threat. And
and listen, I'm I'm no fan of China,
believe me. Truly no fan of China. But
the Chinese do not have an imperialist
history. The Chinese fought a a couple
brief border skirmishes with the
Indians. They fought a brief border
skirmish with the Vietnamese. Aside from
Tibet, which they've always claimed as
theirs, the Chinese don't go around
invading people. They really don't. They
never have. And so, I'm not worried
about a Chinese invasion of uh of
Taiwan. I think that this is a a
creation of the Pentagon
uh for for the purpose of garnering
annual budget increases.
I just don't see any problem with
Taiwan. The Taiwanese don't. They don't
see any problem.
Okay. Speaking of budget increases, can
you touch on Ukraine for a moment? What
what's Last time before you came on, we
were we were preaching getting elected.
We were making some guesses about what
might happen with Ukraine. Seems like
the war is dragging on. Yeah. I don't
know if there's any any hope of it
ending soon, to be honest. What are you
seeing? I don't either. You know,
everybody was Trump said he was going to
he was going to settle this conflict in
24 hours. Nobody believed that. But what
people thought that he would do would be
to cut off uh aid to
Ukraine. And um even that hasn't
happened. Trump, I think, genuinely
believed that Putin would just do what
he told him to do. That the Russians
could keep Donetsk and Luhansk and
Crimea and uh Ukraine would never be
allowed to join NATO, although they
would probably be fasttracked into the
European Union and everybody lives
happily ever after. And that just hasn't
happened. The the Russians just haven't
accepted that deal. And certainly the
Ukrainians haven't accepted that deal.
Trump thought he could force the two
sides to there was a two-hour phone call
between Trump and Putin a couple of days
ago and um and the White House released
a statement saying, "Oh, it was such a
beautiful call. It couldn't have been
any more beautiful and there was love
and respect and and Putin Putin's office
released a statement saying, "Yeah, it
was a good call. We agreed on nothing."
And so now Trump, whether he likes it or
not, is kind of being forced to continue
supplying weapons uh to Ukraine. And the
Germans and the British and the French
are also supplying weapons to Ukraine.
Uh just yesterday
um the the Germans announced that they
would put
um that they would put no
restrictions on how deep into Russian
territory the the Ukrainians could go
with German weapons. That's a that's a
serious uptick. So there there's no
quick down to this war.
Uh it's not good news. No. Is the is the
technology sometimes when I think of
wars and I look back in the history of
wars, I I follow the technology like who
has the ACE? Who who has the SR71 spy
plane or who has what's the deal with
the drones going on over there? feels
like a totally new battleground with
drone warfare now because you can launch
a drone for $1,000. Oh, yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. We're we're in the midst of a of a
real uh shift in war fighting where
we're going to eventually get to a point
where we are, aren't we? Troops Yeah.
troops aren't going to be necessary
anymore. It's all going to be drones.
The thing is, we've got these big badass
drones that carry thousand pound
missiles and, you know, all this stuff.
But but the Iranians, the Ukrainians,
the
Chinese, there are 16 countries that
make drones right now and they make
something called suicide drones. So it's
the drone itself that's the weapon and
the they just fly the drone to crash
into a target. Well, those drones are
cheap and they're small and they're
devastating. So, yeah, it's cool to have
these giant, you know, the Reaper, the
Predator, but uh it's kind of just as
just as good to just crash the drone in
and blow something up.
Well, and you know, I was reading uh the
other day that the Ukraine has actually
gified their drone warfare and that
different teams are getting points. And
so they you get one point for uh you
know getting a single person, you get 50
points for getting a tank, you get 20
points for getting different buildings.
And they said that they actually I think
they tripled the points for individual
uh targets from two points to six
points. And they saw that they saw a
doubling in that week of actual attacks
on individuals to where because then
they're giving the public scores of all
the different drone teams. And so the
drone teams are trying to win in the
public's eye of who has the most points.
And I thought that is just what a world
that we're living in right now where we
are giving points away. Gamifying war.
We're giving war. Just wait until the
PTSD sets in. Then we'll see how
everybody's
doing, man. Yeah. How do you gamify
PTSD? That's not going to be fun.
Seriously.
Yeah. It's it it's sort of like Thomas I
think Thomas Jefferson, if I remember,
he was writing about mosquito boats back
when they were trying to figure out how
big of a navy they wanted and he wanted
tiny little boats. It's like the the
technology finally caught up to where he
could have his dream. We can have these.
They're basically ICBMs that are slow
and they don't hold as much as much
power, but they're just flying kamicazi
explosives. They're cheap. Program them
and have thousands of them. I mean, it's
it's a swarm method. We we you now have
a hive of bees. That's actually a better
way to do war now is with a a beehive
than one big sort of hit. That's right.
Seems like it may it makes me wonder if
communities will have to have their own
like like maybe it'll come to the point
where having a country to have huge
country weapons really isn't what you
need to protect your state or your
community. You need small uh swarms of
drones like is that where we're headed?
And are we moving into it reminds me of
the Matrix where you have EMP defense
weapons? Basically, we all have to start
building EMPs cuz if a swarm of 10,000
100,000 drones is coming at your city,
you can't take them all out with with
with metal. You have to actually blow an
EMP to try and take them all out as much
as possible. And even the the much
vaunted Israeli uh Iron Dome when when
the Iranians launched, I don't know if
you guys remember, this was the first
Iranian response to the Israeli
assassination of a Palestinian leader in
in Tehran. Um, they launched these
drones, but the drones are like flying
in slow motion and they warned the
Iraqis and the Jordanians about
overflight. So, the Israelis had like
six hours before the drones actually
arrived and still seven of them got
through. Seven of them.
So, you're right. This it's the swarm uh
the swarm that is going to win the war.
It sounds crazy that you'd have to have
communities with little drone swarms to
protect you, but it it makes me wonder
like is this what the military is
practicing over in the Sahara when
you're saying that we're at war? Is it
that we need we're going to need
practice with small sort of civilian
forces that are using cheap technology
because it's actually a big threat.
Yeah, that's a good question. We don't
know what's going on in Africa. The
Pentagon won't tell us. So, it's it's
entirely possible. Why are we fighting
in Africa? It doesn't even make Yeah, I
guess I guess I just I'm not educated on
world events, but it's all about seems
like a lot.
Yeah, fight them over there so we don't
have to fight them over here as they
say. Although although we are starting
our own cartel war perhaps. Yeah. What's
the scuttlebutt on what's going on at
the border? Well, you know,
yeah, Trump did that on purpose. I I was
surprised that so much of the media just
missed it. They they said, "Oh, Trump
named the Mexican cartels terrorist
groups. Oh, the how stupid. Now it's
going to go on this list for sanctions."
Now, that wasn't it at all. He did it
because it triggers a release of federal
funds of counterterrorism funds. And so
we weren't allowed to spend money on
drones, on listening devices, on video
intercepts, on tasking NSA. We weren't
allowed to do any of that stuff without
a determination that the cartels were a
terrorist group. And so this isn't about
sanctions. It isn't about border
security. It's about infiltrating these
groups with new federal authorities. I
wouldn't have realized that, John. You
always paint things in a different light
that seems much more informed. Can can
you just can you give like a rundown of
Kil's first 100 days now that we're past
the 100 days? There was so much
speculation on it. Like what do you see
as key failures, key successes, or just
things that he put in motion that will
be long lasting and their effects just
from like the his first few months as
president so far? Well, I think the
thing that's going to be long lasting is
is the advent of the imperial
presidency. We've never
had a
president claim so much unfettered power
in government ever as Donald Trump has.
No, it started with those executive
orders that first round, didn't it? And
you remember they used to criticize
Obama. They said, "Oh, he ruled by
executive order. Uh, what about
Congress? He can't do that." Well, Trump
is dwarfing the executive the number of
executive orders that Obama ever signed
or any other president in American
history.
So I I think this imperial presidency is
something that is here to stay because
unless the Supreme Court starts striking
things down, authorities down, um no
president is going to voluntarily give
up power, you know, voluntarily weaken
the office of the presidency.
Um, so that's I think that's the
big that's the big get that Trump um has
achieved. In other in other things, man,
it's just so much going on. I I fear for
the First Amendment because of the way
he's gone after freedom of speech in um
in universities on the universities.
Yeah, this is very very troubling to me.
But then at the same
time, at the same time, he's done a lot
of things that I wish Democrats had
done. He talks to our enemies. We used
to, we used to mock George W. Bush at
the CIA because we had never seen
anybody work so hard to not speak to our
enemies. He talks to everybody, the
Iranians, Hamas, the North Koreans. He's
happy to have a conversation with
everybody. And that makes the world
safer when he does that. He unilaterally
came to an agreement with the with the
Houthies over the course of a
weekend that essentially ended all
attacks on American shipping. That's
incredible. How come Joe Biden didn't do
that over four
years? So I also like Yeah, it does feel
more like there's a CEO as president,
like someone who just is used to having
board meetings and getting things done.
Grab the bull by the Yep. That's it.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah, I'm I'm willing to give the
guy the benefits of uh Doge.
Oh, I don't think Doge We heard a lot
about it, you know, for the first
hundred days and now it's just not It
feels like it, you know, I know I think
Elon got in trouble because Tesla's
stock went down by 35% and so he kind of
got called back to his corporate
overlords in some capacity. But so with
him not tweeting about it, I mean,
what's your perspective of it? uh what
was your perspective of it while it was
going on and now that it's sort of, you
know, died down in the media, how do you
think it's going now? I got a kick out
of, you know, CIA officers being
escorted out of the building. That was
kind of funny to me. Um, but we've got
the Civil Service Act, which protects
federal workers from exactly this kind
of thing. And they all the people fired
under DOJ have sued. They're going to
win. You can't just fire people just
wantingly. You can certainly have
reductions in force, but that that has
to be governmentwide. Um, and it has to
be, not has to be, but it's almost
always related to the economy. We
haven't had a layoff, a federal layoff
since 1979. That was the last one,
1977. Um, so he went about it the wrong
way. First of all, people are like, who
is this guy? This autistic South African
guy is going to come here and tell me
what to do.
And uh people got tired of that very
very quickly. So I don't think Doge had
any impact on anything or
anybody in a year. People aren't even
going to remember what Doge is. And
you're right has to go back to to uh
protect his $446 billion uh personal
wealth.